Okay we pick up today's דף Daf is י״ט, Yod-Tet, סוטה Sotah
19, and we pick up at the bottom of י״ח עמוד ב׳,
Yod-Chet Amud Bet, and we had just quoted a ברייתא. Braita. Let's
read that ברייתא Braita again quickly just to orient us. The words
are תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. It's about 12 lines from the bottom,
last word on the line. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: זאת תורת הקנאות.
Zot Torat Ha-Kenaot. This is the תורה Torah of jealousies. So the
word תורה Torah is a broadening inclusive word and זאת Zot is
a narrowing and limiting word. מלמד שהאשה שותה ושונה. Melamed Sheha'isha Shota
Ve-shona. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma focuses on תורה Torah to
allow for multiple occurrences. So that tells you that a woman could
be made to drink multiple times after multiple processes. She's suspected and
she drinks once and then another time she's suspected again and warned
in front of witnesses and she could be made to drink again.
תורה Torah means multiple times. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר Omer זאת.
Zot. He emphasizes no, the exclusive, excluding word זאת. Zot. שאין אשה
שותה ושונה. She-en Isha Shota Ve-shona. That she cannot be made to
do it multiple times, only once, no double jeopardy. אמר רבי יהודה:
Amar Rabbi Yehuda: מעשה והעיד לפנינו נחוניא חופר שיחין Ma'aseh Ve-hed Lifneinu
Nechunya Chofre Shichin שהאשה שותה ושונה. Sheha'isha Shota Ve-shona. Somebody testified in
front of this, you know, ditch digger that a woman would do
it multiple times, and there's a question if that means that they
had somehow received a tradition or they had actually claimed that they
had witnessed it. Anyway, either way, that it actually does happen multiple
times. וקבלנו עדותו Ve-kibalnu Eduto and we were willing to accept the
testimony in a limited context. בשני אנשים, Bi-shne Anashim, if it's two
different husbands because two different husbands, if it's the same husband suspecting
twice, you know, maybe the problem here is more with the husband
than with the woman. But two different husbands, that's already a completely
different scenario and therefore it can happen again. בשני אנשים אבל לא
באיש אחד. Bi-shne Anashim Aval Lo Be-ish Echad. וחכמים אומרים: Ve-Chachamim Omrim:
אין אשה שותה ושונה, בין באיש אחד בין בשני אנשים. En Isha
Shota Ve-shona, Ben Be-ish Echad Ben Bi-shne Anashim. So the חכמים Chachamim
here seem to take a more radical position than רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, rejecting even this testimony and saying that a woman can never
be made to drink again, even if it is two different husbands.
Okay, so you have a three-way debate. Now, we could have just
left it at that, but the גמרא Gemara asks a question because
it seems to be based on words in the פסוק Pasuk and
they have to be accounted for, and this question will also lead
to a greater precision on what is being included or excluded. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ותנא
קמא נמי הכתיב זאת? Ve-Tanna Kamma Nami Ha-ketiv Zot? ורבנן בתראי נמי
הכתיב תורת? Ve-Rabbanan Batrai Nami Ha-ketiv Torat? So the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma said that a woman could be made to do it multiple
times. He's only focusing on the word תורת. Torat. Doesn't he have
to account for the word זאת? Zot? Doesn't he have to exclude
something? And the same question in the reverse for the last position.
They say never do it again, but doesn't the word תורת Torat
seem to be including multiple cases? So אמר רבא. Amar Rava. So
רבא Rava lays out the range of possibilities. On one extreme, באיש
אחד ובועל אחד, Be-ish Echad U-vo'el Echad, the same man and she
and this woman is being suspected by the same husband about
the same suspected person that the husband thinks she's having an affair
with. So in that case, it's really double jeopardy. Everything is the
same. He just didn't like the first result so he's going to
do it again, and she's already been proven innocent regarding this man.
So דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאין אשה שותה ושונה. De-kule Alma Lo
Pligi De-en Isha Shota Ve-shona. Everybody agrees no double jeopardy. That is
the word זאת. Zot. That is exactly identical circumstances. Everybody agrees that
that is excluded.
That's one end of the spectrum. Top of י״ט עמוד א׳. Yod-Tet
Amud Alef. בשני אנשים ושני בועלים. Bi-shne Anashim U-shne Bo'alim. On the
other end of the spectrum is all of the circumstances are different:
a different husband and suspected
of having an affair with a different man. So in there, that
case, none of the circumstances are the same. She hasn't been tested
regarding—nobody's in to suspect. It's something having to do with the particular
husband. There has not been any proof through this סוטה Sota test
with this particular paramour or suspected paramour, so everything is different. דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דאשה שותה ושונה, De-kule Alma Lo Pligi De-isha Shota
Ve-shona, that there is double jeopardy—not double jeopardy, that she can go
through the ceremony a second time. דכתיב תורת. De-chetiv Torat. That's the
inclusive תורת. Torat. So everything is the same—one husband, one suspected
adulterer—cannot be tried again (one husband). Everything is different—different husband, different suspected
adulterer—can be—can go through the ceremony a second time. So the first
position is that
the—so the גמרא Gemara says like this: So now let's see how
that plays out with these three. כי פליגי באיש אחד ושני בועלים,
בשני אנשים ובועל אחד. Ki Pligi Be-ish Echad U-shne Bo'alim, Bi-shne Anashim
U-vo'el Echad. They debate the middle cases: two husbands, the same suspected
adulterer, or one husband, two different suspected adulterers. תנא קמא סבר תורת
לרבויי כולהו. Tanna Kamma Savar Torat Lerabbuye Kulhu. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is the most inclusive. You can do it multiple times. I'm going
to focus on the word תורת. Torat. Everything, she can be tried
for again, or a second time I should say. זאת, Zot, the
word זאת, Zot, למעוטי איש אחד ובועל אחד. Lema'ute Ish Echad U-vo'el
Echad. The one case that everybody agreed, that is the one case
that I will exclude: same husband, same suspected adulterer. That is exactly
identical, that not, but everything else yes. That's the extreme of allowing
it to happen multiple times.
ורבנן בתראי, Ve-Rabbanan Batrai, the last rabbis, who say never do it
again.
So סברי זאת למעוטי כולהו. Savri Zot Lema'ute Kulhu. We're going to
say everything cannot happen again except the one extreme case.
תורה לריבוי שני אנשים ושני בעלים. Torah l'ribui shnei anashim v'shnei bealim.
Different husbands, different paramours, in that case, that is something everything is
different we'll allow. So one approach says I'll only disallow whatever everything
is exactly the same. The other approach, the רבנן בתראי, Rabbanan Basrai,
say we'll only allow a second time when everything is different. And
then you have the middle position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי
יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda: זאת למעוטי תרתי תורה לריבויי תרתי. Zot limutei tartei
Torah lirboyei tartei. We're gonna try to balance two cases included, two
cases excluded. זאת למעוטי תרתי, Zot limutei tartei, the two cases that
are excluded: איש אחד ובעל אחד איש אחד ושני בעלים, ish echad
u'baal echad ish echad u'shnei bealim, the same husband, whether suspecting her
of having sex with the same man or with a different man.
If it's the same husband, you don't get tried again. תורה, Torah,
the Torah which says you do get tried again, לריבויי תרתי: lirboyei
tartei: שני אנשים ובעל אחד שני אנשים ושני בעלים. shnei anashim u'baal
echad shnei anashim u'shnei bealim. If it's different husbands, then whether it's
with the same man or with a different man, the fact that
it's different husbands puts it in a completely different set of circumstances.
And you know, this makes sense, right? Since it's about her relationship
with her husband, it makes sense that anything if we're going to
exclude a little bit more broad in the cases we don't allow
a second time, that it'll be cases when it is the same
husband suspecting her again and then also might have more to do
with the husband. But when it's with a different husband, that's already
a completely different set of circumstances and that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says we will allow twice even if she's suspected of having it
with the same adulterer. Maybe you could even say in that case
even more so, you know, why is everybody suspecting her in case
of with this particular man? Alright, anyway, that is the range of
positions. הדרן עלך היה מביא. Hadran Alach Haya Meivi. Now we start
the next פרק, perek, third פרק. perek. היה נוטל את מנחתה מתוך
כפיפה מצרית ונותנה לתוך כלי שרת ונותנה על ידה. Haya noteil es
minchasah mitoch kefifah mitzrit venosnah letoch kli shareis venosnah al yadah. So
he would take, now the question is who's the he? רש"י Rashi
says it means the husband because it's not yet put into a
כלי שרת, kli shareis, only once it's put into a—one of the
temple, you know, sanctified vessels does it become the responsibility of the
כהן, kohen, but the פסוק pasuk speaks about also the כהן kohen
taking it from her hand. So תוספות Tosfos says that this actually
means the כהן. kohen. But he would take the מנחה mincha from—from
this, you know, from this type of a—a wicker basket or you
know, wicker vessel, ונותנה לתוך כלי שרת venosnah letoch kli shareis and
then put it into the holy temple vessel, which would sanctify it.
ונותנה על ידה venosnah al yadah and now it would be placed
on her hand. וכהן מניח ידו מתחתיה, vekohen maniach yado mitachteha, so
she gives it back to her, she's now holding it in this
כלי שרת, kli shareis, it's now been a sanctified מנחה. mincha. The
כהן kohen puts his hand
underneath ומניפה umenifah and you wave it, because the waving both has
to be done with the owners and through the כהן. kohen.
General rule about the—when you wave things, you know, in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. הניף והגיש, heinif vehigish,
so now the כהן kohen after does the waving, he brings it,
he like puts it against the מזבח. mizbeach. קמץ kamatz he takes
the hand-breath והקטיר vehiktir and then, you know, puts the hand-breath onto
the—onto the מזבח mizbeach and it burns up and, you know, he
causes it to—the incense—it—to be offered. והשאר נאכל לכהנים, vehashar ne'echal lakohanim,
and the remainder would be eaten by כהנים. kohanim. This is what
happens with every מנחה: mincha: you touch it to the corner of
the מזבח, mizbeach, you take the hand-breath and you burn that on
the fire and then the כהנים kohanim eat the rest in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. היה משקה ואחר כך מקריב את מנחתה. haya
mashkeh ve'acharkach makriv es minchasah.
Now we're going to see about the order, which has been a
little bit unclear in the משניות. mishnayos. The משנה mishna never did
a simple, you know, step-by-step, they sort of broke it up into
components. And now we're going to discuss the order. So the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says first she would drink and then the מנחה
mincha would be brought. We've seen this position further and only once
the מנחה mincha was brought, then it would sort of trigger the
effect of the water. רבי שמעון אומר מקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך
משקה. Rabbi Shimon omer makriv es minchasah ve'acharkach mashkeh. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon said
no, no, no, first the מנחה mincha then the drinking, which sort
of makes sense because, you know, the drinking is sort of the
dramatic ending of it. שנאמר ואחר ישקה את האשה את המים, shene'emar
ve'achar yashkeh es ha'ishah es hamayim,
and the פסוק pasuk is pretty clear. It says he offers up
the מנחה mincha and afterwards he shall cause the woman to drink
the water. So it's pretty explicit in the פסוק pasuk that that
comes second. אם השקה ואחר כך הקריב את מנחתה כשרה, im hishkah
ve'acharkach hikriv es minchasah kesherah, but I can see, says רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, that if you reversed the order, that—that you first had
her drink and then you did the מנחה, mincha, the מנחה mincha
is כשרה kesherah and then presumably also the—the effect of the waters
would be triggered and would be meaningful once the מנחה mincha was
brought. So what is this debate about? Because it actually, you know,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon quotes actually a פסוק pasuk and it seems
that all of the evidence, you know, should be with רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. So we'll see in the גמרא Gemara because the פסוקים
pesukim themselves are actually quite ambiguous or on this point. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רבי אלעזר לרבי יאשיה
דדריה. amar lei Rabbi Elazar leRabbi Yoshiya d'darei. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
said to רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya of his generation, meaning there was
an older רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiya, but this was a colleague. The
reason the גמרא Gemara emphasizes that this was to רבי יאשיה Rabbi
Yoshiya that was the colleague is because he's going to be talking
to him in a little, you know, sort of instructive way, which
would not be
appropriate to talk to an—an elder in that fashion. So here's what
he said to him. לא תיסיב אכרעך. lo teiseiv akra'ach. Don't sit
down on your legs, meaning I don't want to see you sitting
down. עד דמפרשת לה להא מילתא, ad d'mepharasht lah l'ha miltha, until
you can explain to me this, you know, this following question: מנין
למנחת סוטה שטעונה תנופה? Minayin l'Minchat Sotah she'te'unah Tenufah? So even though
the, you know, thing that attracted us more immediately in the משנה
Mishnah was the question of the order, first we're going to look
at the first part of it, which is the waving. How do
you know that the waving of a מנחה Mincha has to be,
how do you know that the מנחה Mincha of a סוטה Sotah
has to be waved? So מנא לן? minalan? What do you mean
where do we know it? והא כתיב ביה? v'ha ketiv beh? Okay,
it's explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. It says the כהן kohen will
wave it. That's right there in the פסוק. pasuk. So he says,
no, no, בבעיא מנא לן. be'bai minalan. No, I mean how do
you know that the owner of it has to, meaning the woman,
the one who's, it's being brought on her account, how do you
know that she has to be part of that waving as well?
אתיא יד יד משלמים atya yad yad mishelamim because we make a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah from שלמים. shelamim. כתיב הכא ולקח הכהן מיד
האשה, ketiv hacha v'lakach hakohen miyad ha'isha, the כהן kohen should take
from the hand of the woman, וכתיב התם ידיו תביאנה, u'ketiv hatam
yadav tevienah,
his hands should bring, you know, the שלמים. shelamim. And and and
that's written by the owner's hands and it's about the part of
the שלמים, shelamim, the חזה ושוק, chazeh v'shok, the breast and the,
like the leg that would be waved. So מה כאן כהן אף
להלן כהן. mah kan kohen af lehalan kohen.
Now, we actually learn out both directions because there it speaks only
of the owner waving. So by the שלמים shelamim we have a
פסוק pasuk that speaks about the owner waving. And by the מנחה
Mincha we have a פסוק pasuk that speaks about the כהן kohen
waving. So we apply both to both.
מה כאן כהן אף להלן כהן, mah kan kohen af lehalan kohen,
the same way here by the סוטה Sotah it's a כהן, kohen,
same by the שלמים. shelamim. מה להלן בעלים אף כאן בעלים, mah
lehalan be'alim af kan be'alim, and the same way by the שלמים
shelamim we see the owner does the waving, here too as well
by the סוטה Sotah the owner does the waving. הא כיצד? ha
keitzad? And we do this not in two separate acts but in
one joint act. מניח ידו תחת יד בעלים ומניף. maniach yado tachat
yad be'alim u'menif. The כהן kohen puts it under the hands of
the owner and waves it. Makes sense that the owner is the
one that is directly in contact with it because it is like
coming from the owner, it represents, you know, it's connected to the
owner. The כהן kohen is the one that's doing the transition from
the owner to now bring it to the altar. So his hands
are underneath. Okay. Now, הניף והגיש קמץ והקטיר משקה ואחר כך מקריב
מנחתה. henif v'higish kamatz v'hiktir mashkeh v'achar kach makriv minchatah.
Now we get the debate about what is the order. So the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, before we actually look at the question in
the פסוקים, psukim, the גמרא Gemara actually says that the משנה Mishnah
is a little funny because the משנה Mishnah says, you know, it
says הקטיר, hiktir, it says he offered up the קומץ komatz when
it described the steps the כהן kohen took, and then it doubles
back and says oh, first he would have her drink and then
he would bring the מנחה. Mincha. So the גמרא Gemara says הא
אקריבה? ha akrivah? You know, what do you mean? It says you
would offer it up and then you say have her drink and
then offer it up. You just said he offered it up, you
know, he burnt the handful. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי
קאמר. hachi ka'amar. This is how you read the משנה. Mishnah. סדר
מנחה כיצד? seder mincha keitzad? What is the ways of bringing the
מנחה? Mincha? What are the steps that the כהן kohen does? הניף
והגיש קמץ והקטיר. henif v'higish kamatz v'hiktir. You wave it, you touch
it to the altar, you take the קומץ komatz and then you
put it on the fire. והשאר נאכל לכהנים. v'hash'ar ne'echal lakohanim. And
then the rest would be eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. That's what
you do when you bring the מנחה. Mincha. Now we've discussed the
מנחה Mincha and you know and and now let's talk that about
the מנחה Mincha and the water and what are the order and
the relationship there. ובהשקאה גופא פליגי. u'v'hashka'ah gufah peligi. Now regarding when
the drinking takes place, you should be aware that that's a debate.
רבי שמעון ורבנן. Rebbe Shimon v'Rabbanan. ורבנן סברי משקה ואחר כך מקריב.
v'Rabbanan savri mashkeh v'achar kach makriv. The רבנן Rabbanan say first she
drinks and then you bring the מנחה. Mincha. So at מנחה סבר,
Mincha savar, רבי שמעון סבר מקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך משקה. Rebbe
Shimon savar makriv et minchatah v'achar kach mashkeh. No,
first you bring the מנחה Mincha and then she drinks.
שנאמר ואחר ישקה, she'ne'emar v'achar yashkeh, as
the פסוק pasuk says. The פסוק pasuk is explicit. It doesn't just,
it's not just the פסוק pasuk about the drinking comes after. The
פסוק pasuk says, and after this he will cause the woman to
drink the water. Okay. ואם השקה ואחר כך הקריב מנחתה כשרה. v'im
hishkah v'achar kach hikriv minchatah kesherah.
But if רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon concedes that if the order was
reversed, first the drinking and then the מנחה, Mincha, בדיעבד bedi'avad it
would be okay. Now, now we are going to find out how
the חכמים Chachamim could argue on רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon if the
פסוק pasuk is so explicit. And the reason is is because the
פסוק pasuk is explicit but it's also there are multiple פסוקים psukim
and it's confusing. So if you take a look at the פסוק,
pasuk, we have the following.
Okay,
it says, you know, he makes her take the oath. This is
in במדבר ה. Bamidbar hei. Let's start with פסוק כג. pasuk chaf
gimmel. וכתב את האלות האלה הכהן בספר ומחה אל מי המרים. v'chatav
et ha'alot ha'eleh hakohen basefer umacha el mei hamarim. You write it
down and you scrape it in the water. והשקה את האשה. v'hishkah
et ha'isha. You, he causes the woman to drink. He, at מי
המרים המאררים. mei hamarim hamarerim. ובאו בה המים המאררים למרים. u'vau vah
hamayim hamarerim l'marim. And the cursed water should become into, be bitter.
So it says he has her drink. And then it says ולקח
הכהן מיד האשה את מנחת הקנאות. v'lakach hakohen miyad ha'isha et minchat
hakinaut. He takes the מנחה Mincha from her hand. והניף, v'henif, והקריב,
v'hikriv, וקמץ, v'kamatz, all those verbs in our משנה Mishnah are verbs
here in the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, and then it says והקטיר המזבחה
ואחר ישקה את האשה את המים. v'hiktir hamizbeachah v'achar yashkeh et ha'isha
et hamayim. Then he has the woman drink the water. And then
it says again והשקה את המים. v'hishkah et hamayim. He has her
drink the water. והייתה אם נטמאה. v'hayetah im nitme'ah. If she was
טמאה, teme'ah, if she committed adultery, the following will happen to her.
So it says after the waving. After this, he does the water
and then it says he'll drink the water, but it also said
beforehand, he scrapes it into the water and has her drink it.
So how do you deal with those פסוקים? pesukim? What do you
do with that earlier פסוק? pasuk? Okay, and the חכמים chachamim even
privilege the earlier פסוק. pasuk. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן:
Tanu Rabbanan: והשקה. v'hishkah. Okay, that
that is the, that's the פסוק pasuk before the מנחה. minchah. The
first time it says he should have her drink the water. מה
תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? What does this mean? What is it
indicating? והלא כבר נאמר והשקה. v'halo kevar ne'emar v'hishkah. Now it says
והשקה v'hishkah again. Now it says it already said and רש"י Rashi
has a whole discussion about the text, but it means it's going
to say, it's going to say a second time after the מנחה
minchah he will have her drink. What are we to make of
this first והשקה v'hishkah given that the פסוקים pesukim so much emphasize
the drinking afterwards? Okay. שאם נמחקה מגילה ואומרת איני שותה, She'im nimchakah
megillah v'omeret eini shotah, מאיימין אותה ומשקין אותה בעל כרחה. ma'imin otah
u'mashkin otah b'al karchah. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, the point of והשקה v'hishkah is not
to tell the first one is not to tell you when. It
says the כהן kohen scrapes it into the water and he causes
her to drink the water. That doesn't mean now he causes her
to drink the water. That's going to be after the מנחה. minchah.
But it means once it's scraped in the water, then we're going
to ensure then you know, come heck or high water, we're going
to make sure she drinks it. It's being scraped in order that
she should drink it. והשקה V'hishkah is like in order that she
should drink it and we're going to make sure she's going to
drink it, but it's not saying that now is when you do
it. But it's in the context of the fact that it was
scraped. To teach you that once it is erased into the water,
even if she does not want to, you like, you know, you
you stir up, you unsettle her and get her to drink it.
Even against her will. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. Okay, but
the real order is that it's going to be after the מנחה.
minchah. רבי שמעון אומר ואחר ישקה מה תלמוד לומר? Rabbi Shimon omer
v'achar yashkeh mah talmud lomar? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it says
afterwards have her drink. What does that teach you? והלא כבר נאמר
והשקה, v'halo kevar ne'emar v'hishkah, he should have her drink, אלא לאחר
כל המעשים כולם האמורים למעלה. ela l'achar kol hama'asim kulan ha'amurim l'ma'alah.
After everything that was said above. So what does this mean exactly?
So this is really the continuation of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon work jointly. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says the first והשקה v'hishkah is not when it happens,
but the importance of the scraping in the water and the fact
that we're going to ensure that that happens eventually. And רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says now that it says ואחר ישקה, v'achar yashkeh, that
is to tell you that now is the time. After the מנחה
minchah is brought, this is when the time that actually the drinking
takes place. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואחר ישקה והלא כבר נאמר
והשקה אלא לאחר כל המעשים כולם האמורים למעלה. v'achar yashkeh v'halo kevar
ne'emar v'hishkah ela l'achar kol hama'asim kulan ha'amurim l'ma'alah. Only after you
do everything that was said above because clearly the פסוקים pesukim are
indicating the order. Then you do the drinking. What are the things?
מגיד ששלשה דברים מעכבין בה. Maggid she'shloshah devarim me'akvin bah. Three things
have to come before the drinking takes place. עד שלא קרב הקומץ.
Ad shelo karav hakometz. Number one, the thing that's being debated in
the משנה. Mishnah. First the קומץ, kometz, the handbreadth has to be
offered, the מנחה minchah has to be offered beforehand. Although we'll say
בדיעבד, b'di'eved, but certainly at the, you know, the way it's supposed
to be בדיעבד b'di'eved you could reverse the order but the way
it's supposed to be done is the handbreadth has to be offered.
ועד שלא נמחקה מגילה V'ad shelo nimchakah megillah
and you also can't have her drink until you erase because it
was also mentioned earlier in the פסוק pasuk you scrape off the
words and then you have her drink. Of course the גמרא's Gemara's
going to ask it's not physically possible to drink it if it
hasn't been scraped in. But okay, now we're focusing on the פסוקים.
pesukim. The פסוקים pesukim said first scraping then the drinking, so that
also has to be first. ועד שלא תקבל עליה השבועה. V'ad shelo
tekabbel aleha hashuah.
And also you have to do that he causes her to take
the שבועה, shvuah, right that even you know and she says אמן
אמן. amen amen. All those things are prerequisites before the drinking of
the water. ואחר V'achar is very clearly placing the drinking at the
very end.
Okay. עד שלא קרב הקומץ. Ad shelo karav hakometz. Now the גמרא's
Gemara's going to analyze all these three things. So the first point
it has to come after the מנחה. minchah. רבי שמעון לטעמיה. Rabbi
Shimon l'ta'ameih. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going according to his reasoning.
דאמר מקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך משקה. De'amar makriv et minchatah v'achar
kach mashkeh. Okay,
that's exactly the משנה. Mishnah. First the מנחה minchah then the drinking
exactly as the פסוקים pesukim indicate. עד שלא נמחקה מגילה. Ad shelo
nimchakah megillah.
Now number two, you can't drink before you scrape the words in.
You erase the מגילה. megillah. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי
משקיה לה? ela mai mashkeh lah? Of course you can't, it's not
physically possible. What are you going to have her drink if the
ink hasn't been scraped in? So אמר רב אשי לא נצרכא אלא
לשירומי ניכרא. Amar Rav Ashi lo nitzrecha ela l'shirumi nichra. No, no,
what it means is it has to be fully scraped in. Let's
say you scrape the words in and you still have some marks
on the page and you can still see you know a faded
version of the words. It didn't get fully scraped. The water won't
work. It has to be fully erased. Okay, so you can have
a place where it was erased but not fully erased.
Okay, so and ועד שלא תקבל עליה השבועה. v'ad shelo tekabbel aleha
hashuah. So and the third thing is is that she cannot drink
until she's done the שבועה, shvuah, she accepted the שבועה. shvuah. So
the גמרא Gemara says that sounds like משתו דלא שתיא מיכתב כתיבא.
mishtu de'la shatya michtav ketiva. It sounds like she just can't drink
before she's done the שבועה shvuah but that the מגילה megillah could
be written. But it sounds like you know you could do everything
else you could write the מגילה. megillah. והאמר רבא מגילת סוטה שכתבה
קודם שתקבל עליה שבועה לא עשה ולא כלום. V'ha'amar Rava megillat sotah
shektavah kodem shetekabbel aleha shvuah lo asah v'lo klum. Did not רבא
Rava say that if you wrote it before she accepted the שבועה
shvuah it didn't it doesn't count at all? Right, the order of
the פסוקים. pesukim. So it comes, he makes her take the oath,
she takes the oath, he writes down the words and then he
scrapes it in. That order has to be very precisely followed, so
you know it's not just that the oath has to be before
the drinking, the oath has to be before the writing. So the
גמרא Gemara says כדי נסבה. kedi nasba. Okay, you're right, that was
just thrown in, you know, to get three, because three is a
much better number than two. There are three important points I want
to make here. The human brain operates at that three is a
very worth good word for remember number for remembering more than two
and more than four. The גמרא Gemara often says שמע מינה תלת,
shma mina tlat, we can understand you know we learn out from
this case three things, and often תוספות Tosafot says wait, those three
really boil down to two. So it's sort of like here. Sometimes
you just want to get three. All right, anyway, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: Okay, so that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. When the פסוק pasuk says והשקה vehishka earlier
just means for the purpose of having her drink, but the order
is the drinking comes at the end. במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflegi? Now
going back to our משנה, Mishnah, we have a רבי שמעון/רבי עקיבא
joint position. What is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon against the חכמים? chachamim?
Why did the חכמים chachamim in the משנה Mishnah say that the
drinking comes first? What do they do with ואחר ישקה את האשה?
ve'achar yashke et ha'isha? So let's take a look. What do they
debate? תלתא קראי כתיבי. tlata kray ketivei. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to look at the three פסוקים psukim that we've been
discussing. והשקה קמא, vehishka kama, the first והשקה vehishka before the מנחה
mincha is brought, ואחר ישקה ve'achar yashke then after the מנחה mincha
is brought it says afterwards the woman should drink, and then והשקה
בתרא, vehishka batra, and then it says again and he shall shall
drink the water. רבנן סברי והשקה קמא לגופו דמשקה ואחר כך מקריב.
Rabbanan savri vehishka kama legufo demashke ve'achar kach makriv. So the rabbis
say, I'm going to go with the תנא קמא, Tanna Kama, even
though the פסוק pasuk says afterwards the woman will drink the water,
I am going to follow you know if it says drink the
water the first time it says it, that's when it means it.
The water is you know gets drunk here, before the מנחה mincha
is brought. That's what it says in the פסוקים, psukim, והשקה vehishka
and only afterwards it talks about the מנחה. mincha. ואחר כך מקריב
מנחתה. ve'achar kach makriv minchata. ואחר ישקה, ve'achar yashke,
so what about it says afterwards he shall have the woman drink
the water? מיבעי ליה שרשומו ניכר. miba'ei lei sherishumo nikkar.
That's just to tell you a separate הלכה, halacha, not to tell
you the order, but it's telling you after you've by the way,
okay you had her drink the water, you had her bring the
מנחה, mincha, let's double back for a minute, you know, the drinking
of the water can only be after you fully do everything that
came before it, meaning, going back to the point we said before,
you have to fully scrape the מגילה, megilla, you can't have some
you know pale writing left behind. So it's really telling you a
parenthetical point, everything that came before the water has to be done
before you drink the water, but actually it's the water and then
the מנחה. mincha. והשקה בתרא, vehishka batra, now what about the last
והשקה? vehishka? It says והשקה hishka twice after the מנחה mincha and
nevertheless the rabbis are saying neither of those are telling you order.
שאם נמחקה מגילה ואמרה איני שותה מערעין אותה ומשקין אותה בעל כרחה.
she'im nimchaka megilla ve'omra eini shota me'arin otah umashkin otah be'al karchah.
That's to tell you the teaching of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva So
we חאפ chap in the two teachings of the previous ברייתא, braita,
the רשומו ניכר rishumo nikkar and the teaching of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. Okay, which is to tell you again drink the water means
there's going to be times we're going to force her to drink
the water once it's been erased even if she says she won't,
we basically force her to. So yes, we learn out three things
from the פסוקים, psukim, but the same three things as it were,
but we're going to focus on the first והשקה vehishka to tell
you that comes first, even though again the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים psukim very much militates against that. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says that's the רבנן. Rabbanan. ורבי שמעון סבר לא ואחר
ישקה לגופו. veRabbi Shimon savar lo ve'achar yashke legufo. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says I don't care that ואחר ישקה ve'achar yashke is not
the first time it says drink. It's very explicit, after this you
drink. That's the literal one, that's telling you the order. First the
מנחה mincha then the drinking. לגופו דמקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך משקה.
legufo demakriv et minchata ve'achar kach mashke. He first the מנחה mincha
and then she drinks. והשקה קמא, vehishka kama, how about the first
והשקה? vehishka? And now we're getting back to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Actually
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. says that means that we would force her.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has a different version, this is to get
his position in the משנה Mishnah of בדיעבד. bediavad. שאם השקה ואחר
כך הקריב את מנחתה כשרה. she'im hishka ve'achar hikriv et minchata kshira.
Okay,
that if it could be it will work if he does it
now. So it's almost like it says you know he scrapes it
in והשקה את המים vehishka et hamayim even if you were to
והשקה את המים vehishka et hamayim now we could still go forward
and you could bring the מנחה, mincha, but really ואחר ישקה את
האשה את המים. ve'achar yashke et ha'isha et hamayim. The real drinking
should be afterwards. So it says והשקה hishka before to tell you
that at least בדיעבד bediavad it works. All right, והשקה בתרא, vehishka
batra, now the last והשקה? vehishka? That goes back to רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva שאם נמחקה מגילה ואמרה איני שותה מערעין אותה ומשקין אותה
בעל כרחה. she'im nimchaka megilla ve'omra eini shota me'arin otah umashkin otah
be'al karchah.
That's to tell us that you know we're going to make her
drink it. There'll be a time when we're going to actually force
her to drink it and we won't take no for an answer.
So you have the ואחר ve'achar to be the literal after, והשקה
vehishka earlier to tell you בדיעבד bediavad it'll work if it comes
before the מנחה mincha and the last one to tell you there
are times just going to make sure that this happens. Okay,
רבנן בדיעבד לא פתח קרא. Rabbanan bediavad lo patach kra. And the
rabbis say no, I refuse to accept that, even though it says
ואחר ישקה, ve'achar yashke, the פסוק pasuk would not begin with the
בדיעבד bediavad case, mentioning the drinking before the מנחה. mincha. Because it
mentions drinking before the מנחה, mincha, it must be that that is
the לכתחילה lechatchila case. So you know it might have been better
if he would have read
it's better פשט *pshat*, it just means he should have erased it
in order that והשקה ve-hishka *ve-hishka* we're going to ensure that והשקה
*ve-hishka*. Okay, but that's why they push back against רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* because he reads this as a בדיעבד *bedieved*. Okay
now, וסבר רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. מטלין אותה בעל כרחה *V'savar Rabbi
Akiva matilin otah b'al korcha*? Now, in this ברייתא Baraita *braita* we
quoted, not in the משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, we said רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* said you'd do it against her will. Is that
really רבי עקיבא'ס *Rabbi Akiva's* position? והתניא *V'hatanya*, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
אומר קלבוס של ברזל מטלין לתוך פיה *Rabbi Yehuda omer kalbos shel
barzel matilin l'toch piha*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* said that you would
put like a metal, you know,
a
metal hook like made of, you know, an iron sort of thing
to keep the mouth open, to wedge, to force the mouth open,
something like, you know, in the jaws to separate the jaws. They
would put into her mouth, שאם נמחקה מגילה ואמרה איני שותה, מערערין
אותה ומשקין אותה בעל כרחה *she-im nimchaka megilla v'amra eini shota m'arin
otah u-mashkin otah b'al korcha*. Because in the case where after the
מגילה *megilla* was erased, she said, "I'm not going to drink," we'll
force her jaws open with this metal device and we'll force her
to drink. אמר רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Amar Rabbi Akiva*, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* said, "כלום אנו צריכים אלא לבודקה *klum anu
tzrichim ela l'vodka*? Wait, no, I don't agree with that. The purpose
of erasing God's name... I understand you're saying like God's name shouldn't
have been erased for naught, and if we're already going to erase
God's name then it has to have been for a purpose so
we're going to force her to drink. And that... but רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says, "But look, the purpose was served. The
fear of the water got her to admit. So we've achieved the
purpose." The only reason we're doing this is to test and to
see whether she committed adultery. והלא בדוקה ועומדת *v'halo beduka v'omedet*. So
she's admitting that she did it. So okay, the waters achieved their
goal. Why are we going to force her, you know, just because
the name was erased? אלא *Ela*, so rather רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva* says, עד שלא קרב הקומץ יכולה לחזור בה, משקרב הקומץ
mishekarav hakometz, אינה יכולה לחזור בה *ad she-lo karav ha-kometz yechola lachzor
ba, mishe-karav ha-kometz eina yechola lachzor ba*. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva,
*Rabbi Akiva* interestingly does concede for some reason... and the question's why
is this going to be any different? Once the קומץ kometz *kometz*
was brought, then she can't say no, then we're going to force
her to drink, again having the drinking come later. Before it, she
can say no. So the question is I don't get it, same
point, once she's saying that she refuses to drink she's implicitly admitting,
so the waters have served their purpose. Why do you, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, make a distinction before after the מנחה mincha
*mincha* is brought? Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says... you know, so anyway this was brought as a
proof that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* rejects the idea of
forcing her. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* pushes back: What do you
mean? It's very clear he holds forcing her, just at a different
time. ולטעמיך *u-l'tamecha*, according to you, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, תיקשי
לך היא גופא *tikshe lach hi gufa*. You know, the ברייתא *braita*
itself doesn't make sense. משקרב הקומץ אינה יכולה לחזור בה *mishe-karav ha-kometz
eina yechola lachzor ba*. That רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says, you know,
yeah you're right, we are going to force her, but only after
the קומץ *kometz* was brought. והלא בדוקה ועומדת *v'halo beduka v'omedet*. So
you know, but she's already base- implicitly confessed. So if that's what
he holds before the קומץ *kometz*, he should hold it after. So
let's first understand, you know, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* does hold you
force her, he just draws the line in a different place. Let's
understand why he's drawing the line here.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. לא קשיא: הא דהדרה בה
מחמת רתיתא, והא דהדרה בה מחמת בריותא *lo kashya: ha d'hadra bah
machamat retita, v'ha d'hadra bah machamat briyuta*. The question is, is her
you know saying she won't drink, is that really an implicit confession?
You know, maybe we've just done such a good job at terrifying
her that she's going to refuse to drink even though she's innocent.
So that's the case we're concerned about. If we knew that she
was implicitly admitting it, certainly everybody agrees that if she says "I
am guilty" that we don't make her drink, then we all agree
even though the name was erased, it's it's served its purpose, she
admitted. So the question is do we in her saying "I refuse
to drink", רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says "I am not sure I
always hear in that her admitting her guilt." It depends what the
context is. If she's like trembling and the fear is obvious, so
you know, people out of fear don't aren't thinking rationally and therefore
it might not be an admission of guilt, we just really you
know scared the bejesus out of her. But if however she's calm
and collected and says "I'm not going to", then it's we understand
that that's implicitly she's not terrified, she understands what's at stake here
and she doesn't want the water to do their job. So whether
it's an implicit admission depends on whether it's out of fear or
out of a calm disposition. Okay so let's take a look. והכי
קאמר *V'hachi ka'amar*. Here's what רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says. כל מחמת
בריותא כלל כלל לא שתיא *Kol machamat briyuta klal klal lo shatya*.
Whenever she is doing it when he rejects the position of רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that we force her, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says,
"Look, if she's refusing to do it in a calm, collected way,
then we do not force her. That is an implicit admission. So
I will never force her that case." That's when he sounds categorical.
However, there are cases I'll consider it and I will do it,
but that depends on the following. רתיתא *Retita*, if she's trembling, then
already it's not necessarily an admission and here's where I'm going to
draw the line. עד שלא קרב הקומץ *ad she-lo karav ha-kometz*, before
the קומץ *kometz* is brought, דאכתי לא נמחק מגילה *d'achti lo nimchak
megilla*. That number one, it might be before the מגילה *megilla* was
even erased. But that's not really the point. אינמי נמחקה מגילה דלא
כדין עבדי כהנים kohanim דמחקי *inammi nimchaka megilla d'lo k'din avdi kohanim
d'machki*
or that the מגילה *megilla* was... was scraped, but the כהנים kohanim
did not do the right thing, because they erased it. So what
does this mean the כהנים kohanim did incorrectly? I mean the פסוקים
pesukim have it being erased and then the מנחה mincha being brought,
but what רש"י Rashi explains is that since רבי עקיבא is of
the position that, you know, there are going to be, well since
everybody sort of feels we don't want the name, God's name to
be erased in vain, so we want to delay the erasing as
much as possible. So, so basically, yes the מנחה mincha. and the
erasing have to happen before the drinking, but the erasing doesn't happen
before the מנחה. mincha Again, not the order of the פסוקים. pesukim.
So the גמרא here is assuming, as רש"י Rashi explains, that it
should be מנחה mincha and then erasing. Okay, and therefore in this
case the כהנים erased before the מנחה mincha was being brought. Okay,
so in that
case דשלא כדין עבוד כהנים דמחקי, deshelo kedin avud kohanim demachkei, they
shouldn't have erased it before the מנחה mincha was being brought, מצי
הדרה בה. matzi hadra bah. So she has her fear, it might
not be an admission, and anyway, you know, she had more time
available to her and the reason she doesn't have this time is
because the כהנים jumped the gun. So therefore we will allow her
to back out without forcing her to drink. משקרב הקומץ,
but once the קומץ was offered and then it was erased, דבדין
עבוד כהנים דמחקי, devedin avud kohanim demachkei, everything was done properly that
they erased, לא מצי הדרה בה. lo matzi hadra bah. There we
are, there because she's trembling we think that we cannot assume that
this is an admission, she just might be irrationally afraid and therefore,
ironically, because she's afraid we're going to force her to drink because
we can't implicitly assume it's an admission. So what do we have?
We have a debate. רבי יהודה says we'll always force her. רבי
עקיבא says if she's calm it's an admission and we won't. Everybody
agrees when it's an explicit admission we won't. Okay, if she's trembling
it depends, before or after the מנחה based on whether we erased
it a little bit too soon. So now, and that's why רבי
עקיבא earlier also was able to say that we sometimes force her
from the word והשקה because he concedes that there are cases we
force her. קשיא דרבי עקיבא אדרבי עקיבא, Kashya de-Rabbi Akiva ad-Rabbi Akiva,
so now, okay, the two רבי עקיבא though, the first ברייתא we
quoted and this, don't exactly agree on what the line was. התם
אמר מחיקה מעכבא, Hatam amar mechika me-akva, in the earlier place he
said that as soon as it's erased, here it says מעכב me-akev
but it means, you know, that determines whether or not she's going
to drink. As soon as it's erased we're going to force her
to drink. והכא אמר קומץ מעכב, Vehacha amar kometz me-akev,
and here he says that only after the burning of the hand-breath
are we going to force her to drink. And also here at
least the way the גמרא understands it, he makes a distinction between
calm and nervous. תרי תנאי ואליבא דרבי עקיבא. Trei tanna-ei ve-aliba de-Rabbi
Akiva. Fine, there's a debate of תנאים Tanna-im where רבי עקיבא's line
was in terms of forcing her to drink. איבעיא להו, Iba-ya lehu,
now they ask the following question. אמרה איני שותה מחמת ביעתותא וחזרה
ואמרה שותה אני מהו. Amra eini shota machmat biyututa ve-chazra ve-amra shota
ani mahu.
Let's say the woman is calm and collected and she says I'm
not going to drink. And now רבי עקיבא, you know, maybe she
waited until now because she thought her husband wasn't going to get
to this point. Okay, but now רבי עקיבא says okay then that's
an implicit admission. All right, so she says I'm not going to
drink. וחזרה ואמרה שותה אני, ve-chazra ve-amra shota ani, and then she
says, you know what, I changed my mind, I am going to
drink. מהו, Mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? Do we let her drink?
כיון דאמרה איני שותה טמאה אני קאמרה, Keivan de-amra eini shota tmeia
ani ka-amra, since she's saying I'm not going to drink she's implicitly
saying that she has committed adultery, that's at least the way רבי
עקיבא reads it. וכיון דאחזיק נפשה בטומאה לא מצי הדרה בה, Ve-keivan
de-achzik nafsha be-tuma lo matzi hadra bah, once she established herself that
she had committed adultery she can't retract it. You know, that's an
interesting question in general about a wife admitting that she committed adultery
to her husband and the implications when somebody says this is my
הלכתי halachic status that you start to get like stuck with that.
The fact that the גמרא uses the word like דאחזיק, de-achzik, you
know, somehow there's a whole question here about are we sort of
making this a judicial procedure and it didn't sort of use more
הלכתי halachic איסור issur status like you established the הלכתי halachic status
of something to be, rather than she testified against herself. Normally you
can't testify against yourself. So anyway because she established her status, therefore
she cannot retract it. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say,
כיון דאמרה שותה אני גליא דעתא דמחמת ביעתותא הוא דאמרה, keivan de-amra
shota ani galya da-ata de-machmat biyututa hu de-amra,
or no, maybe once she said I'm going to drink it shows
you that no matter how much somebody looks calm and collected, you
don't really know why they're saying they're not going to do it.
Is it because they're guilty or is it because even with their
innocence, you know, they're afraid. So and now maybe that she's prepared
to do it, you see that that wasn't really an admission, she
didn't say it explicitly, so in hindsight we're not going to read
it that way and we are going to let her drink. תיקו,
Teiku, we don't know. אמר אבוה דשמואל Amar Avu d'Shmuel says the
father of שמואל, Shmuel, צריך שיתן מר לתוך המים. Tzarich sheyitein mar
letoch hamayim. The water has to actually, you have to take something
bitter, some bitter tasting, you know, additive into the water. מאי טעמא
דאמר קרא מי המרים המרים כבר. Mai ta-ama de-amar kra mei hamarim
hamarim kvar.
It says she shall, you know, scrape it into the bitter waters
and not, and it also has מאררים me-arerim that cause curse, but
what makes them bitter? So he says the bitterness is not, is
not, what do you call it, is not because of the curses
that were scraped in, the bitterness is independent of it and that
had to already be. מרים כבר. marim kvar. It says she shall
scrape it into
the bitter waters and it also has מאררים meararim that cause curse.
But what makes them bitter? So he says the bitterness is not
because of the curses that were scraped in, the bitterness is independent
of it, and that has to already be bitter. Okay, so we
will end here at the משנה.